孩子是无辜的
The boy is blameless.
这才是我的女人
That's my girl.
该死
Cack!
你还好吧？一副杀气腾腾的样子
You all right? You're looking pointy.
奥斯提亚那边有什么消息？
What's the news from Ostia?
亚历山大港那边来了三船谷物 穆萨的人运来的
Three grain ships from Alex in. Mussa's people.
来杯酒吧 提提神
Have a cup of wine. Set you up.
照25的价格收费 不能再少了
Take 25, no less.
把装船的活儿给阿贾克斯
Give the lading to Ajax.
啊 恐怕穆萨要抱怨了
Well, Mussa will complain.
他敢 我割了他的舌头
If he does, cut out his tongue.
你以为我在开玩笑？
You think I'm joking?
我这就去处理
I'll see to it now.
乌瑞纳斯
Vorenus...
没事儿
Nothing.
西莲地区的曼米欧来了
Memmio of the Caelian is here.
他想见见你
He asked to see you.
你好 曼米欧
Salve, Memmio.
请坐
Please sit down.
天气变了啊 我还是喜欢暖和一点
Weather's turning. I like a bit of heat.
你来艾文台有什么事 曼米欧？
What brings you to the Aventine, Memmio?
不兜圈子 直切主题 我喜欢这样
No chitchat. Straight to cases. I like that.
我手下卡尔波的一个侄子
A young nephew of my colleague Carbo here
被一个艾文台的人给玷污了
was defiled by an Aventine man.
他的名字是昆特斯·布波 你认识他吗？
Name of Quintus Bubo. You know him?
我认识他
I know him.
如果你允许的话 卡尔波希望 能为了家族的荣誉进行报复
With your permission, Carbo wishes to avenge his family's honor
- 干掉这个昆特斯 - 那孩子才12岁
- and kill this Quintus. - The boy's only 12.
他为了钱去帮人吹箫
He was sucking his cock for pennies.
这么说他是收了钱的？
He was paid, then?
是的 他没有先来问过我
Yes, but he didn't ask me first.
这孩子收了酬劳了
The boy was paid.
我家的人不经我允许不能去干这种事
Nobody in my family sucks cock without I say so.
卡尔波也算是有名望的人
Carbo is from respectable people.
那孩子拿了人家钱
The boy took money.
他干得是妓女的活儿
He was working as a prostitute.
昆特斯·布波没有对你不敬 不许碰他
Quintus Bubo's committed no offense. You won't touch him.
乌瑞纳斯 我的兄弟 也许你误解了
Brother Vorenus, perhaps you misunderstand.
我没误解什么 兄弟
I misunderstand nothing, brother.
我从马克·安东尼那里直接受命维持和平
I've been given strict mandate by Mark Antony to maintain the peace.
昆特斯·布波是个有头有脸的人
Quintus Bubo is a man of property and respect.
你们不准碰他
You will not touch him.
不管有没有算上钱的事 他占了那孩子的便宜
Money or not though, he took advantage of the boy.
也许给他适当的惩罚…
Perhaps some moderate form of punishment...
我们是已经忍不下去了才来找你的 这只不过是走个形式
We come to you out of politeness. A mere formality.
我已经给了你们回答了
I've given you my answer.
这答案根本就他妈是错的
Wrong fucking answer.
这只蛆虫玷污了我的名声 和我家族的荣誉
This maggot pisses on my name, on my family honor.
管好你的手下 曼米欧
Control your man, Memmio.
乌瑞纳斯 这人说得有道理
Vorenus, the man has a fair point.
闭嘴 波罗
Silence, Pullo!
乌瑞纳斯 我的兄弟 坦率地说
Brother Vorenus, in all candor,
就连你自己的人都明白…
even your own man knows...
我的人不明白什么时候该闭嘴
My man doesn't know when to keep his mouth shut.
我已经告诉你们我的决定了
I've given you my decision.
那么我们很荣幸地接受你的裁决
And we graciously accept your judgment.
耽误你的时间了
I thank you for your time
我为这小小的争端道歉
and I apologize for the disruption.
你用不着当着这么多人侮辱我…
You didn't have to insult me in front of...
绝对不要在别人面前质疑我的权威
Do not question my authority in front of others.
任何时候都不要质疑我的权威
Do not question my authority under any circumstances.
权威？
Authority?
当老大不容易吧？
Hard being the boss?
真是好东西
Good stuff.
是吗？这东西感觉如何？
Is it? How does one tell?
试试就知道
Try.
屏住呼吸
Hold your breath.
好可怕
It's horrid.
稍等片刻 就会感觉十分美妙
In a minute, you'll feel delicious.
你认识乔卡斯塔
You know Jocasta.
我认识吗？
Do I?
- 我们去年剧院里见过 我当时陪着 - 你们在干什么？
- We met at the theater last year. I was with... - What are you doing?
我们在吸大麻
We're inhaling hemp.
我看得出来
I can see that.
你们让整间屋子臭气薰天
You're making the whole house stink.
- 以后 如果你非要吸 就到外面去 - 好的 母亲
- In future, do it outside if you must. - Yes, Mother.
- 这东西好用吗？- 简直一流
- Is it any good? - Excellent.
拿过来
Give it here.
我从马其顿带了两袋子回来
I brought back two sacks from Macedonia.
比意大利货好多了
So much better than the Italian kind.
马其顿？
Macedonia?
嗯 我爸爸在那儿有个采石场
Papa has quarries there.
等安东尼任期结束之后 我们也会去那儿
We're going there when Antony takes up his governorship.
- 那儿情况怎么样？- 我亲爱的 那儿真是吓死人
- How's there? - My dear, it's ghastly.
天气混浊不堪 食物难以下咽 人如同野兽一样
Filthy climate, vile food, beastly people.
- 也许你没有融入上流社会 - 啊 不是的 爸爸很有钱
- Perhaps you didn't mix in the best society. - Oh, no, Papa is hideously rich,
不过那里没什么上流社会可言
but there's no society to be found.
那儿的男人喜欢干自己的羊
The men are overly fond of fucking their sheep.
如果你见过那儿的女人 也就没理由责备他们了
And when you meet the women, you can hardly blame them.
那儿绝对是世界末日
It truly is the end of the world.
我并不是个势利眼 奥克塔维娅
I'm no snob, Octavia,
你带商人的女儿回家我还不介意
and I don't mind that you bring home a tradesman's daughter...
可是标准就不要再往下降了 好吗？
but let's just stop there, shall we?
别带演员 或者角斗士 或是这之类的人 懂吗？
No actors, no gladiators, or that sort of thing, ne?
别理她
Don't mind her.
自从屋大维走了之后 她就变得跟恶鬼附身一样
She's been an infernal grump since Octavian left.
找人去问问安东尼 他什么时候回家 不 算了
Send to ask Antony when he's coming home. No, don't.
管他呢
A fig for him.
好的 女主人 泰门正等着
Yes, domina. Timon is waiting,
他问你是不是能见见他
asking if it pleases you to see him.
女主人
Domina.
- 女主人 - 走吧
- Domina... - Go away.
- 但是玛如拉说 - 我改变主意了
- But Merula said... - Changed my mind.
嘿 杜罗
Hello, Duro.
噢 爽啊
Yes, it's good.
真爽
It's good.
太好了
Very good!
早啊 阿爸 我们在学希伯莱文
Hello, Abba. We're learning Hebrew.
- 我看见了 - 他们很快就可以读经文了
- I can see that. - They'll be reading Torah in no time.
我都等不及了
I can't wait.
昨天晚上你回来得相当迟啊
You came in very late last night.
公事
Business.
花天酒地 耳鬓厮磨的公事
Business involving wine, vomit and sex.
真抱歉 难道我让你心烦了吗？
I'm sorry, did I disturb you?
不 一点也不
No, not at all.
不过在你上来弄我之前记得先把我叫醒
But do please wake me before you come at me so.
会让人感觉不那么…
It would be a little less...
受惊吓
alarming.
我在想关于马其顿的事
I was thinking about Macedonia.
是吗？我们一定得去吗？
Were you?
难道我们不能留在这儿吗？
Do we have to go? Can't we just... stay here?
不行
No.
等我的任期一结束 我们就走
Once my consulship is over, we're gone.
可是那儿离罗马太远了
But it's so far from Rome.
那儿也有裁缝
They have dressmakers
和珠宝商 在那不毛之地和在这儿都一样
and jewel merchants in Odessa just like here.
一旦你离开意大利
Once you're gone from Italy
你的敌人就不再害怕你了
your enemies will no longer fear you
你会再也没力量击垮他们
and you will be powerless to strike at them.
我不想击垮他们
I don't want to strike at them.
这儿已经没什么油水可捞了
There's no juice in it anymore.
我只要和平与安宁
I want peace and quiet
以及一个供我掌控的富饶的小省份
and a nice rich province to squeeze.
和平与安宁？
Peace and quiet?
当你在马其顿大灌黄汤 你认为布鲁图斯和卡西乌斯会不管？
While you're swilling wine in Macedonia, will Brutus and Cassius be idle?
那些无助的可怜虫？
Those abject creatures?
当你把握权力时才显得无助
Abject only while you have power.
你的敌人可是要到你死了才会罢手
Your enemies will not rest until you are dead.
你现在是骑虎难下 不能就这么放手了
You have a wolf by the ears. You cannot let go of him now.
把油递给我 好吗？
Pass the oil, would you?
回避
Make way!
谢谢 太谢谢你了
Well, thank you. Thank you very much.
我们下个礼拜再见面 嗯 好的
We'll see you next week? Yeah.
- 我的兄弟 - 那人是谁？
- Brother! - Who was that man?
- 哪个？- 你刚刚说话的那个
- Who? - The man you were speaking with.
噢 你是说巴拉克 他是个香料商
You mean Barak. He's a saffron trader.
我觉得可不像
Doesn't look like a saffron trader.
又不是所有人都表里如一 对吧
Not everybody looks like what they are.
公正 公会长
Justice, Captain!
- 我乞求公正 - 这是谁？
- I beg for justice! - Who's this?
昆特斯·布波和他的妻子
Quintus Bubo and his wife.
昆特斯被曼米欧的手下给阉割了
Gelded by Memmio's boys.
求求你 公会长 给我们主持公道
Please, Captain, justice!
好了 冷静下来 兄弟
Come on. Calm down, brother.
那老家伙不该若无其事地到处溜达
He shouldn't have been goating around.
- 曼米欧违背了我的命令 - 他至少没有干掉那个老傻瓜
- Memmio disobeyed me. - He didn't kill the old fool at least.
- 他违背了我的命令 - 让我去跟曼米欧说说
- He disobeyed me! - Let me go talk to Memmio.
- 我会进行调解的 - 不用
- I'll sort out a compromise. - No.
如果你为了这么点小事就惩罚卡尔波
If you punish Carbo over this trivia,
曼米欧会认为你不尊重他
Memmio is going to take it as disrespect.
他会报复的 你将挑起一场黑帮大战
He'll retaliate. You'll start a gang war.
很有可能 但是我别无选择
Very likely, but I've got no choice.
- 而且这都是你的错 - 什么？这怎么成了我的错？
- And it's your fault. - What? How is it my fault?
你当着曼米欧的面质疑了我的权威
You questioned my authority.
- 这让他有了理由违背我的命令 - 胡扯
- That gave him license to disobey me. - Oh, bollocks.
现在 你要去找卡尔波
Now, you go and find Carbo.
把他对我表示出的不敬还给他
You show him the same disrespect that he has shown me.
- 大家都有错 - 我是在命令你
- Everyone is in the wrong here. - I gave you an order.
这里又不是军营 我不听任何人的命令
This isn't the mumpin' Legion. I take orders from no man.
那么你对我就没用了 你 去做吧
Then you're no use to me. You, go and do it.
我会的 头儿
Will do, Captain.
你完全想岔了
You are thinking all backwards.
我警告过你不要质疑我的权威 你了解自己的地位
I warned you about questioning my authority. You learn your place.
我的地位？去你妈的混帐东西
My place? Well, fuck you, you miserable bastard,
是我一直护着你活下来
I'm the one trying to keep you alive.
除了挑起黑帮大战你什么都不想 是吧？
You'd love to start a gang war.
你尽管去找死吧 了结你所有的怨气
Get yourself killed. Put an end to all your misery.
让半个城市给你陪葬
Take half the city with you.
让我来告诉你 你可以死上一千次
Well, I tell you what. You can die a thousand times.
也不可能让内奥比 或者孩子们或者恺撒活过来
And it won't bring back Niobe or the children or Caesar!
听着 我是你的朋友 我只是想帮你
Listen, I'm your friend. I'm trying to help.
- 你从来没有帮助过我 - 我没有？
- You've never helped me. - Have I not?
那么是谁一次又一次救下你的性命？
Well, who saved your life a dozen times?
是谁料理了那个卑鄙的伊万德？
Who took care of that snake Evander?
你喝醉了是谁把你扶回家？
Who carried you home when... when you were drunk?
你什么意思？
What do you mean?
什么“料理了伊万德”
"Took care of Evander."
没事 什么意思都没有
Nothing... I didn't mean anything.
你什么意思？
What do you mean?
说呀
Speak.
是我杀了他
I killed him.
我知道他做的事情之后就杀了他
I found out what he'd done and killed him.
听着 她爱的是你
Listen, she loved you.
你们俩在一起才是幸福的 如果我告诉了你 你也会杀了他
You were happy together. If I'd told you, you would have killed her.
出去
Get out!
我还能怎么做？
What was I supposed to do?
滚出去
Get out.
阿提娅还好吧 我想
Atia thrives, I trust?
是的 是的
She does. She does.
家里其他人呢？
And the rest of the family?
都挺好的
Good enough.
他真是个让人吃惊的孩子 不是吗？
Yes, a surprising boy, isn't he?
屋大维 这么小的孩子就这么有冲劲
Octavian. Such vim and vigor for one so young.
他们说他召集的军队数量可是相当地庞大
They say it's a considerable army he's raised.
从平原上买些傻子瘸子
Buying up all the fools and cripples in Campania
可组建不了一支军队
is hardly raising an army.
你是对的毫无疑问
You are right, no doubt.
不过里面也有不少老兵
But many are veterans also.
第八军团 还有第七军团的人
Eighth Legion men. Seventh Legion.
那些人光拿钱不干活
Sat on their backsides taking his money
等他走过时就欢呼“万岁”
to cheer him as he goes by.
恺撒他算个屁
Caesar my arse.
不过我叫你来不是为了谈小孩子的事
But I didn't bring you here to talk of children.
当然 我洗耳恭听
Indeed, I await your pleasure.
当我执政官的任期满了之后
When my term as consul is over...
我不想再要马其顿的控制权
I no longer wish to take the governorship of Macedonia.
我要高卢
I wish to take Gaul.
但是德奇姆斯才是高卢的统治者
But Decimus is Governor of Gaul.
要是他喜欢 就把马其顿拿去好了
Well, he can have Macedonia if he likes.
我要的是高卢 那儿天气更好
I want Gaul. The weather's better.
我恐怕这有点难度
I'm afraid that will be a bit difficult.
元老院恐怕会忖度你打算仿效恺撒
The Senate may suppose you plan to emulate Caesar,
陈兵边境
camping your legions on our border.
靠近罗马
Close enough to Rome
威胁我们好让你为所欲为
to scare us into doing anything you wish.
别慌 我可从来没这么想
Steady on. Hadn't even crossed my mind.
我只不过比较喜欢高卢
I just prefer Gaul.
但你也应该理解为什么元老院
But you understand why the Senate
会拒绝通过这个提议
would not pass such a measure?
你不就是元老院吗 西赛罗
You are the Senate, Cicero.
下次元老院开会时
The next time we meet,
也许你就该提议让我接管高卢
perhaps you will propose my governorship of Gaul.
没有人会惹麻烦的 如果有德高望重的西赛罗支持我的话
No one can make any trouble if the noble Cicero is backing me.
我不认为这是个好主意
I don't think that's a good idea.
倒不是我不愿意助你一臂之力
Not that I do not wish to help you...
作为朋友
as a friend.
但是元老院会认为我支持你
But the Senate would know I was backing you
只不过是因为怕死
only through... through fear of death.
啊 我明白了
I understand.
你不想给人当成胆小鬼
You do not want to seem cowardly.
告诉他们我贿赂了你
Well, tell them I bribed you.
你肯接受贿赂吗？
Would you accept a bribe?
我不能
I would not.
哦 钱太多了 是吧？
Rich enough?
不过至少值得说来一试
Well, it's always worth a try.
那么 你让我只剩下唯一的选择
Well, you leave me only one option, then.
最后总会走到这一步
It always comes to this.
我知道了
I know.
真抱歉
I'm sorry.
我们一起度过了多少时光啊
Such times we live in.
那就来吧
Please, go on.
尽管威胁我吧
Make your threats.
我可不愿因为一点点暗示就屈服
I don't like to submit to mere implication.
有个问题我一直都想问你
There is a question I've always wanted to ask you.
你的老朋友 克拉苏
Your old friend Crassus,
帕提亚人俘虏他的时候
when he was captured by the Parthians,
他们是不是真的 把融化的金子倒进了他的喉咙？
is it true that they poured molten gold down his throat?
因为那样真的会很痛
Because that would really sting.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你说的是对的
It is correct, what you say.
马其顿那儿的天气确实有点
The weather in Macedonia is...
恐怖
dreadful.
我以为你还想多知道一点
I thought maybe you'd want to know a bit more
- 我提到的事情 - 我不想
- than what I said. - I don't.
你应该知道内奥比没有… 她没有…
You should know Niobe wasn't...
不许提她
Don't speak of her.
那都是过去的事 已经结束了
It's in the past. It is done.
兄弟 我很抱歉要对你隐瞒
Brother, I'm sorry I kept it from you.
我认为那是为你好 我很抱歉
I thought it was for the best. I'm sorry.
我原谅你了 兄弟
I forgive you, brother.
我理解你为什么不告诉我 我理解
I understand why you didn't tell me. I understand.
- 我听到你说的了 但是… - 我是说真的
- I hear you say that, but... - I mean it.
我原谅你
I forgive you.
我怎么能不原谅你呢 波罗？
How could I not forgive you, Pullo?
你是我生命里剩下的一切了
You're all I've got left in life.
一直让我活命的人 啊？
Keeping me alive?
说到那个 跟西莲那帮人的事
This business with the Caelians...
- 怎么了？- 我们还是可以阻止开战的
- What of it? - We can still stop it turning into a war.
让卡尔波付一笔罚金
Let Carbo pay a fine.
如果我悄悄去跟曼米欧谈
If I go and talk quietly to Memmio
事情能解决也没有人会丢面子
we can sort it out so that no one loses face.
你以前就说过了
You suggested that before.
值得去做 总比开战好
Worth a go. Better than a war.
也许你是对的 也许
You may be right. You may be.
不过现在太晚了
But it's too late now.
出去
Move.
你好吗 卡尔波
Salve, Carbo.
拎起来
Get him up.
不
No!
告诉你的女主人我有她儿子的口信
Tell your mistress I have a message from her son.
活见鬼
Piss and blood!
请原谅我的冒昧 我是被获准进来的
Forgive the intrusion. I was entranced.
你是谁？
Who are you?
我是玛尔库斯·维普撒尼乌斯·阿格里帕
I am Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa,
凯撒的朋友
a friend of Caesar...
就是屋大维
of Octavian as was.
您是他的姐姐奥克塔维娅吗？
Have I the honor of speaking to his sister Octavia?
是 我弟弟来了吗？
Yes. Is my brother here?
没出什么事吧？他还好吗？
There's nothing wrong, is there? He's all right?
不… 是的
No... Yes.
我是说 不 他没来 是的 他一切都好
I mean, no, he's not here. But yes, he's well.
我5天前出发的时候 他还活蹦乱跳的
I left him five days ago, thriving.
很快乐
Happy.
- 他让我替他问您好 - 没有信吗？
- I am to convey his best wishes to you. - No letter?
我告诉他该写封信 但您知道他的脾气
I told him he ought to write, but you know how he is.
请坐
Please.
虽然没有写信 但他让我转告您 他还是一如既往的爱您
In place of writing, I am charged to tell you that he loves you as ever
并且让我回答任何您提出的问题
and to answer any questions you may have,
只要不牵涉到政治机密
consonant with political security.
他自大的毛病一点没改
He's grown no less pompous, then?
现在的生活比起读书来更适合他
It suits him better now than at school.
他是个有能力的人
He's a powerful man.
人人都这样说 但我就是不敢相信
So everyone says. I cannot believe it.
我的小弟弟
My little brother.
您的小弟弟现在领导着一支拥有1万名壮丁的军队
Your little brother has an army 10,000 strong.
我差不多给他写了100封信了 要他停止这愚蠢的行为
I have written him a hundred times asking him to stop this madness.
- 但他就是不听 - 相反的
- But he does not listen to me. - On the contrary.
我认为在这世界上 您是唯一说话他会听的人
I think you are the only person in the world he does listen to.
他是信使？他叫阿格里帕
Is this the messenger?
是屋大维的朋友
This is Agrippa, a friend of Octavian.
很荣幸见到您
Deeply honored.
怎么说？
And so?
他让我确定你们一切都好
He asked that I make certain you're well,
并让我转达他对你们的敬意和忠诚
and to assure you of his respect and fidelity.
我们好的很
We're very well.
至于他的敬意和忠诚…
And as for his respect and fidelity...
他请求您为家族的名誉着想
He begs that in the name of family
将眼光放得远一些
you keep an open mind as to your future prospects.
你千里迢迢从坎帕尼亚过来就是说这个？
You came all the way from Campania to say that?
- 我还有别的任务 - 什么任务？
- I have other business. - With whom?
我有权利不说
I am not at liberty to say.
搞阴谋诡计吧？
Intrigue, is it?
我猜你是带头的吧
I imagine you're a master.
马克·安东尼知道你在罗马吗？
Does Mark Antony know that you're in the city?
我猜执政官不可能知道每个市民的行踪
I expect there are many citizens whose location is unknown to the Consul.
是啊 但他应该会想知道
True, but he does like to know
- 叛国者们的行踪 - 母亲
- where the traitors are. - Mother!
他们是叛国者不是吗？
Well, they are traitors, aren't they?
安东尼是罗马的执政官
Antony is consul in Rome,
而屋大维蓄意要绊倒他
and Octavian is deliberately challenging him.
如果他不算个叛国者 我不知道他能算什么
If this is not a traitor, I don't know what is.
我该说的都说了
I have said what I must.
请您准许我离开
I will take your leave to go.
告诉我儿子我…
Tell my son I...
不 我没什么和他说的
No, tell him nothing.
派人去通知安东尼 玛尔库斯·阿格里帕在罗马
Send to tell Antony that Marcus Agrippa is in the city.
母亲 不要
Mother, no!
谁知道安东尼会对他做出什么事来
Who knows what Antony will do to him?
反正不会是什么好事
Nothing pleasant, I would think.
他是你儿子的朋友
He is your son's friend.
我没有儿子
I have no son.
嘿 艾泰亚 亲爱的你好吗？
Althea, my honey. How goes it?
- 你知道他们不允许你进厨房的 - 但我饿了
- You know you're not allowed in the kitchen. - But I'm hungry.
你不会告发我的吧？
You won't tell on me, will you?
你该尝尝
You should try some.
我们在等你
We've been waiting for you.
等你们的吧 宝贝 你的女主人在哪儿？
Keep waiting. Where's your mistress?
- 女主人不会来 - 我要和她说话
- Never mind about my mistress. - I want to speak to her.
她不会和像你这样的人说话
She doesn't speak to the like of you.
我也不会和像你这样的人说话
And I don't speak to the like of you.
她要我办事就要出来见我
She wants the job done, she'll see me.
你直接和我说
You speak to me.
那改天好了
Maybe some other time.
等等
Wait.
这么说你就是赛维莉娅？
So you're Servilia, then, are you?
没说的 真是没说的
Choice. Very choice.
你敢再直呼我的名字
Address me by my name again
我会把你的舌头钉在车轮上
and I'll have your tongue nailed to a wagon wheel.
原谅我 我没和贵族说过话
Forgive me. I've not spoken to nobility before.
- 他叫什么？- 杜罗
- What's his name? - Duro.
艾伦尼说的没错
Eleni was right.
你是个漂亮的小家伙 不是吗？
You're a pretty little man, aren't you?
你混进优利亚家里已经有段时间了
You've been in the house of the Julii for some time now.
为什么阿提娅还活着？
Why is Atia still alive?
时机还不成熟
Trouble's finding the right time.
她们一直一块儿吃饭 她和她女儿
They always eat together, her and the daughter.
- 如果你不介意把那个小妞 一块儿干了 - 我明天就干
- If I can kill the young cunny - I can do it tomorrow.
不要伤害那个女孩
No. No harm to the girl.
好吧 如果我能在安东尼的鸡巴上下毒 事情就好办多了
Well, then, if I could only put the poison on Antony's cock, we'd be sweet.
女主人每餐必吃
The domina dines on that regular.
可惜不行 所以你得耐心点
Failing that, you'll have to be patient.
你只有这些愚蠢的笑话告诉我
You have only foul jokes to tell me.
- 那你来干什么？- 雪克尔（古罗马钱币） 女王
- Why are you come here? - Shekels, queen.
- 雪克尔 - 他要钱
- Shekels. - He wants money.
他没有拿到钱吗？
Has he not already been paid?
办这事儿花的时间比我们预计的要长
The job's taking longer than we thought.
多劳多得不是吗？
Let's be fair.
给他
Give him what he asks.
我要300
Make it 300.
等一下
Wait!
我走之前吻我一下
Give me a kiss before I go.
- 你说什么 - 吻我
- Excuse me? - Kiss me.
不可能
I don't think so.
你要不要那个女人死？吻我
You want this woman dead? Kiss me.
[比西尼亚省（东土耳其）]
很有趣
That's very good.
那么我们回到钱的问题上来吧 尊贵的陛下 请您好好考虑
So if we could return to the subject of money... please bear in mind, Your Excellency,
那些帮助我们的人 将来也会得到罗马的帮助
that those that help us now will have good friends in Rome
一旦叛国者马克·安东尼倒了台 你们就能和罗马结盟
when Mark Antony, the traitor, is deposed. Very good friends.
这只是时间问题 不管您是否帮助我们
It's only a matter of time. With or without your help,
我们都要组织军队
we shall raise an army.
我们要
We shall.
安东尼的头烂在木钉上
Antony's head will rot on a spike.
罗马女人被狒狒操
There are Roman women who are fucked by baboons.
什么？
Excuse me?
我听说有那种表演
I've heard there are shows where such things can be seen.
实际上那不能说是表演 那是一种惩罚
They're not so much shows, really. They're more a punishment.
我很愿意见识一下
I should like to see that.
比西尼亚这儿可没有这个
We do not have such in Bithynia.
我认为只要训练一下狒狒就可以
I should imagine it's simply a matter of training the baboons.
我们这儿没狒狒
We have no baboons here.
一种猿类都没有
No apes of any kind.
哦 我没注意到
I wasn't aware of that.
那么就像我刚才说的 现在帮助了我们…
So as I say, those who help us now...
对 你要我出钱帮你们组织军队
Yes, you want my money to raise an army.
那就要让我看罗马女人被狒狒操
I want to see a Roman woman fucked by baboons.
也许我们能安排一下的
Perhaps arrangements can be made.
我杀了他 就是我
I killed him. I did.
我必须杀他
I had to.
这是我们家族的天性
You know, it's in my blood.
我的祖先杀死过暴君塔奎因
My ancestor dethroned the tyrant Tarquin.
我想当时有不少人 都捅了你们的凯撒吧
I understand there were a great many who stabbed your Caesar.
我捅了最后的一刀
I delivered the final blow.
听上去有点像懦夫 不是吗？
Seems a bit cowardly, no?
你说什么？
You say what?
他已经受伤了 一个人垂死挣扎 毫无反抗之力
He was wounded already-dying, defenseless, alone.
可你还去捅了他一刀
And you stabbed him yet again.
他是个暴君
He was a tyrant.
我们杀他是应该的
Our killing him was a necessity.
是必须的 神圣的行为
A necessary and noble act.
也许我该找具新鲜尸体捅几刀
Perhaps I shall find a fresh corpse to stab
- 没准也能成伟人 - 什么？你敢侮辱我
- and become great myself. - What, you dare to insult me?
- 抱歉 - 你敢侮辱罗马元老？
- Excuse me. - A senator of Rome?
站起来
Stand up.
- 站起来 - 布鲁图斯 我们该出去透透气
- Stand up! - Perhaps we should get some air?
不 这个人… 这条狗侮辱了我
No, this man... this dog insults me.
狗 他是这么说的吗？我是狗？
Dog, he says? I'm a dog?
原谅我们 酒精作用 热昏了头 我们是来做客的
Excuse us. It's the wine, the heat.
- 我们是来求他们帮忙的 - 求他们帮忙？
- We are guests here! - Looking for favor.
我才不要求这些野兽帮忙
Favor? I ask no favor of such animals.
收敛些 笨蛋
Control yourself, you fool.
他说我是懦夫
They called me a coward.
过来 过来
Come with me. Come on.
我是元老
I am a senator.
- 我的朋友 你无路可走了 - 别管我
- My friend, you have lost your way. - Leave me alone.
- 布鲁图斯 - 别管我
- Brutus... - Leave me alone!
对不起
I'm sorry.
边洗边喝？坏兆头
Wine in the bath? Bad sign.
你又晚了
You're late again.
把期望放低点 亲爱的
Revise your expectations, my dear,
- 你就会发现我每次来的都很早 - 你收到我的口信没有？
- and I will always be early. - Did you get my message?
哪个口信？
About?
关于屋大维派来的人 玛尔库斯·阿格里帕
Octavian's man Marcus Agrippa.
哦是的 是的 我知道他的事
Oh, yes, yes. I know all about him.
- 那你抓了他没有？- 没必要
- Well, did you catch him? - There's no need.
但他不怀好意
But he's up to no good.
我很清楚他来干什么
I know exactly what he's up to.
屋大维派他来和西赛罗秘密会谈
Octavian sent him to meet with Cicero,
- 希望和他结盟反对我 - 然后呢？
- hoping to form an alliance against me. - Well, then?
西赛罗不会答应
Cicero will refuse.
他的小命在我手里
I have my foot on his throat.
我很愿意你儿子知道这一点
And I'm happy for your son to know it.
阿格里帕可以自由进出罗马
Agrippa can come and go as he pleases.
你会怎么对付屋大维？
What will become of Octavian?
哦 你别操这份心了
Don't worry yourself.
我不会伤害他
I'll not harm him.
发誓
Swear it.
我指着朱庇特神的石头发誓 他是我的家人
On Jupiter's stone. He's family.
如果被抓住 我们会被钉死的
If they catch us, they'll crucify us.
帮我看着点守卫
Watch for the guard.
我出去后就把卢西尔斯传给我
When I get through, you pass Lucius to me.
嘿 过来
Hey, come here.
莱蒂 莱蒂
Lyde! Lyde!
莱蒂 不 莱蒂 莱蒂
Lyde, no!
盖娅 帮我一下
Oh, Gaia, give me a hand here.
你自己的尿自己端
Carry your own piss.
贱女人 真该给你几鞭子
Bitch pig whore. See how you like a whipping.
确定是曼米欧干的吗？
Are we sure that it's Memmio's work?
他嘴里含着西莲公社的硬币
Caelian coin in his mouth.
把人集合起来
Call armed assembly.
这下好了
Here we go.
那么你的意思是我们就当没事发生？
You think we should ignore this, I suppose?
不 你想要开战 好了 我们现在必须打了
No, you wanted a war, you got it. We have to fight now.
你不认为你该去和曼米欧谈谈吗？也许他会同意妥协
You don't think you should go and talk to Memmio? Find a compromise?
晚了
It's too late for that.
他当然会听你的 不是吗？
Surely he'd listen to you, wouldn't he?
你的意思是说我和曼米欧是一伙的？
Are you saying I'm with Memmio?
我没说 你自己说的 变得比水星还快
I didn't say it, you did. Quick as Mercury.
兄弟
Brother...
兄弟 你看不出你的变化吗？
Brother, can't you see what's happening to you?
不 我看不出 兄弟 我变什么了？
I can't see it, brother. What is happening to me?
我变什么了 你能看清楚而我自己看不清楚？
What is it that you can see so clear that I can't?
魔鬼 你被魔鬼占据了 我说不出其他的
A demon. A demon has possessed you or I don't know what.
这么说你看到魔鬼了？他长什么样？
You see a demon, is it? What does it look like?
问问你自己 我和曼米欧？
Listen to yourself, man. Me and Memmio?
你怎么会那么想？我是你的朋友
How could you think that? I'm your friend.
我爱你 我永远不会背叛你
I love you. I would never betray you.
对我说谎 背着我杀人
Lying to me, going behind my back.
- 不是那么回事 - 不是吗？
- It was never like that. - It wasn't like that?
告诉我 你很享受和我老婆搞在一起吧
You tell me, did you enjoy fucking my wife?
什么？你不告诉我那件事
- What? - Is that why you didn't tell me,
是因为你和她也有一腿是不是？
because you were fucking her?
你有点过分了
You have stepped over the line.
我搞过我老婆没有？我在问你问题
Did you fuck my wife? I am asking you a question.
- 让开 - 我在问你问题
- Get out of my way. - I am asking you a question!
我说什么还有意义吗？你不会相信我
What can I say? You won't believe me.
- 你说实话我就会相信 - 我指着我母亲的尸骨发誓
- If you tell the truth then I will believe you. - On the bones of my mother,
我和内奥比之间什么事也没有 从来没有
there was nothing between me and Niobe. Nothing, never.
我不相信 说实话
I don't believe you. Tell me the truth.
好吧 我操过她 满意了吗？
All right, I fucked her! All right?
我操过她 我和这山上一半的男人都操过她
I fucked her! Me and half the men on the hill.
你一出门我们就上她
Any time you were away, bang!
她一直张着腿 门口排着长队
Legs open, line at the door.
不会吧
Come on.
没事吧
Are you all right?
别碰我 别碰我
Don't touch me. Don't touch me.
我们现在去哪儿？
Where are we going now?
不知道 随便哪儿
I don't know. Anywhere.
只要离开这个鬼地方
Away from this damn place.
圣詹纳斯神
Divine Janus,
黑夜过去 白昼降临
as this day follows the night,
求你使我的生命重新开始
let me start my life anew.
如同大浪冲刷沙滩
As the shore is scoured by the tide,
求你洁净我
let me be cleansed.
如同种子开花结果
As the seed becomes the flower,
求你使我重生
let me be born again.
对不起 我迟到了吗？
I'm so sorry. Am I late?
我们已经点过名了 到会人数已达到法定人数
We have completed taking roll. A quorum exists.
好极了
Excellent.
那我们开始吧
Then let us begin.
不 事实上 还不能开始
No, actually, not quite yet.
看来西塞罗来的比我还晚啊
I see that Cicero outdoes me in his tardiness.
很遗憾西赛罗病了
Cicero is regrettably ill
不能参加这次会议
and unable to attend this session.
但是他有个重要的提案
But he has an important matter to propose
关于我接管高卢的事
regarding my governorship of Gaul.
要我亲自派轿夫去请他来吗？
Should I send my litter bearers for him?
他有交待这事 并交给我一份讲稿
He did, however, provide me with a speech
他坚持一定要宣读
that he most urgently insisted be read into the rolls.
好吧 不管怎么说 让我们听听尊贵的西赛罗说些什么
Well, then, by all means, let us hear the words of mighty Cicero.
以下的话来自 玛尔库斯·图里乌斯·西赛罗
These being the words of Marcus Tullius Cicero
年轻时 我为祖国而战
"When I was a young man, I defended our state.
现在我老了 仍然不会离弃祖国
"As an old man, I shall not abandon it.
我衷心地感谢马克·安东尼
"I give sincere thanks to Mark Antony,
因为他慷慨的给予支持
"who has generously presented me
使得我的仕途一帆风顺
"with the most promising theme imaginable.
以下的话是给安东尼的
"I address you directly, Antony.
希望你听这些话的时候…
"Please listen as if you...
的时候…
"as if you..."
念下去
Go on.
希望你听这些话的时候
"Please listen...
能够保持清醒和理智
"as if you were sober and intelligent
而不是一个被酒精和性欲冲昏头脑的废人
"and not a drink-sodden, sex-addled wreck."
当然你也不是毫无建树
"You are certainly not without accomplishments.
年纪轻轻就搞到破产
"It is a rare man who can boast of becoming a bankrupt
倒也不是一般人能做到的
"before even coming of age.
你带来了战争
"You have brought upon us war,
瘟疫和毁灭
"pestilence and destruction.
你是罗马的灾星
"You are Rome's Helen of Troy.
所以…
"But then...
"But then..."
念下去
Go on.
Go on!
把你比做特洛伊的海伦 是最适合不过了
"...a woman's role has always suited you best."
记下来
Write a note.
致屋大维 还是写凯撒吧
To Octavian... Caesar, rather.
告诉他我和安东尼撕破脸了
Tell him I have exposed Antony
他是个背信弃义的卑鄙小人
for the debauched rat he is.
如今 共和国将感恩戴德
At this time, the Republic would be most grateful to accept
如果凯撒愿意提供帮助
Caesar's offer of assistance.
我们需要他立即派兵
We shall need his army at once.
[3个月后]
在高卢
In Gaul,
叛乱者马克·安东尼率军围困了
the renegade Mark Antony has laid siege
穆提那城
to the city of Mutina.
但援兵即将抵达那里
But salvation is at hand!
元老院已经派出了军队
The Senate sends an army
由将军希尔提乌斯和潘撒率领
led by the generals Hirtius and Pansa.
贵族先锋 年轻的凯撒·屋大维
The noble patriot, young Caesar Octavian,
也率领着他的军团加入我军
joins our generals with his own legions
他们将把叛乱者撕成碎片
to crush the rebels.
好不容易走到马西里亚
So much traveling. All the way to Massilia,
现在又大老远的跑回来 我们真是有病
now come all the way back. Crazy.
对不起宝贝 没办法
Sorry, love. Had to do it.
诸神让我和乌瑞纳斯反目
The gods have me vexed over Vorenus.
不和他和解我心里总有个疙瘩
I can't go on until I sort things out with him.
费不了什么事
That's all.
解决完了我们就走
Then we'll be on our way again.
出什么事了？
What's happened?
有人吗？
Anyone home?
- 波罗 - 马修斯
- Pullo! - Mascius.
这儿怎么了？
What's all this?
稀客 真没想到还能见到你
Expecting visitors. I never thought I'd see you again.
我也是
Nor I you.
你回来太好了 我们急需人手
Anyroad, it's good to have you home. We need every man we can get.
我们不打算留下 我只是来找乌瑞纳斯 他人呢？
We're not stopping. I just came to talk to Vorenus. Where is he?
他不在 什么时候回来？
Well, he's not here.
我不知道 他走了
When is he back?
他和马克·安东尼去了北部
I don't know. He's gone. Went north with Mark Antony.
- 北部？- 走了几个月了
- Went north? - Months ago.
安东尼带着他的军队 准备去拿下高卢 乌瑞纳斯一起去了
Antony gathered his troops and set off to take Gaul.
安东尼亲自来召他一起去
Vorenus went with him. Asked for special by Antony himself.
把这个烂摊子留给了我
He's left me in charge of a right old mess.
自从我们搞了卡尔波
Ever since we gave Carbo one up the arse,
西莲那帮人就没消停过
Caelian boys and their friends have been going at us like Belgians.
上个月我们损失了10个人
We lost ten men this month.
- 来吧 你确定你不要留下？- 什么？
- Come on, are you sure you're not stopping? - What?
不了 不 我只是来找乌瑞纳斯的
No. I just came to talk to Vorenus.
现在怎么办？
What now?
不知道
I don't know.
我想不通
I don't understand it.
诸神在耍我
The gods are playing tricks.
他们说:回罗马 找乌瑞纳斯谈谈
"Go back to Rome," they say. "Talk to Vorenus."
如今他们又让我见不着他
Then they hide him from me.
我照做了
I did as I was told.
他不在这儿 就是不在
If he's not here, he's not here.
我可以留封信给他
I can leave him a letter.
亲爱的乌瑞纳斯 我没有搞过你老婆
"Dear Vorenus, I don't fuck your wife."
差不多吧
Something like that.
我们离开好吗？
Let's be going.
离开意大利
Best get out of Italy.
看上去又要内战了
A civil war is coming again, looks like.
你们罗马人啊
You people.
去艾文台是往这儿走吗？
Is this the way to Aventine...
波罗
Pullo!
你认不出我了？
Don't you know me?
莱蒂？
Lyde?
对
Yes.
我是莱蒂 我是莱蒂
I'm Lyde. I'm Lyde.
你活着 你真的活着
But you're all right. You're all right.
- 谢谢 - 你去哪儿了？
- Thank you. - Where have you been?
孩子们 孩子们还活着
The children! The children are alive!
奥克塔维娅去哪儿了？
Where's Octavia?
和乔卡斯塔一起出去了
Out with Jocasta.
太棒了
Excellent.
我总算能吃顿安生饭了
I shall finally be able to enjoy my dinner in peace.
- 这是什么？- 海胆 女主人
- What is this? - Sea urchins, domina.
我不想吃这个 还有什么？
I don't care for it. What else is there?
薄荷炖鹅肉加蔬菜
A savory stew of goose and root vegetables.
给我那个
Bring me that.
还没走？
Still here?
舍不得你啊宝贝儿
Can't get enough of you, my love.
过来
Come here.
去吧
Go on.